A Guide to the Papers of the Twin Oaks Community,
Special Collections, University of Virginia Library
- Series 1: Councils
  - H. Income Council
    - Income Council. Hammocks. Shop, 1981-1989, 21 items. (Box-folder 7:6)
      Proposal for hammock production and other issues like storage and braidmaking; floor plan of new hammocks office.
    - Income Council. Hammocks. Stretchers, 1978-1989, 6 items. (Box-folder 7:7)
      Notes on processing stretchers for hammocks; opinion and idea papers; meeting notes.
    - Income Council. Income Statements, 1983-1987; 1991, 15 items. (Box-folder 7:8)
      Income statements.
    - Income Council. Macramé, n.d., 15 items. (Box-folder 7:9)
      Photographs and negatives; information on macramé kit.
    - Income Council. New Industry Crew. Chimney Brushes, 1984-1987, 18 items. (Box-folder 7:10)
      Catalog of chimney brushes; updates on status of chimney brushes; evaluation for producing chimney brushes; application for change in space use; meeting reports proposal; letter from business.
    - Income Council. New Industry Crew. Computer Software, 1986-1990, 7 items. (Box-folder 7:11)
      Proposals and progress reports.
    - Income Council. New Industry Crew. Herb Gardening, 1981, 3 items. (Box-folder 7:12)
      Proposal for starting an herb plant selling business; opinion and idea papers.
    - Income Council. New Industry Crew. Indexing, 1982-1988, 17 items. (Box-folder 7:13)
      Progress report; opinion and idea papers; instructions; application for space use; letter to clients such as the State Department; publication of an article in Choice on indexing titled "Chelsea House: Modern Critical Views," May 1987; planning budget worksheet.
    - Income Council. New Industry Crew. Kibbutz Industry, 1976-1977, 12 items. (Box-folder 7:14)
      Correspondence with the University of Haifa.
    - Income Council. New Industry Crew. Video Reproduction, 1987-1988, 4 items. (Box-folder 7:15)
      Proposals and information on copying VHS tapes for a non-profit consortium.
    - Income Council. New Industry Crew. Widgets, 1983-1984, 22 items. (Box-folder 7:16)
      Widget template; correspondence with businesses on custom ordered cabinets; sketches of a custom cabinet; new industry proposal; information and updates on widgets; photographs of a numeric keyboard.
    - Income Council. New Industry Ideas, n.d., 7 items. (Box-folder 7:17)
      Magazine clippings on small businesses, solar hardware, and canneries; notes on money-making projects with small capital.
    - Income Council. New Industry Proposal Forms, 1977, 7 items. (Box-folder 7:18)
      Proposals on sewing baby carriers, truck gardening, and typesetting; list of criteria compiled by the New Industry Crew.
    - Income Council. Outside Work/Odd Jobs, 1974-1987, 16 items. (Box-folder 8:1)
      List of services available by the Twin Oaks Community; update on members working outside of Twin Oaks; policy on outside work and odd jobs; request for odd jobs; information on "The School of Living;" financial report; letter to planners.
    - Income Council. Pig Manure, 1979-1980, 14 items. (Box-folder 8:2)
      Drafts and final agreement of manure contract with Carlsons for transporting and disposing of pig manure; termination of contract.
    - Income Council. Product for Friends, 1979-1988, 8 items. (Box-folder 8:3)
      Policies; notes on products to give as trade or gift; PFF member list.
    - Income Council. Reports, 1981-1987, 6 items. (Box-folder 8:4)
      Various financial reports; packets on product information.
    - Income Council. Taxes, 1977-1989, 20 items. (Box-folder 8:5)
      Tax policy; opinion and idea papers on taxes; agreement for the Louisa alternative fund and escrow account; 1998 budget request worksheet; letter to IRS; updates and notes on the court case Twin Oaks vs. IRS; reading on taxes and religious and apostolic associations.
  - I. Office Council
    - Office Council. Accounting. Budget, 1986-1988, 8 items. (Box-folder 8:6)
      Information on petty cash voucher; financial advisor and control reports; planwriting budget worksheet; cash variance paper; money budget report.
    - Office Council. Accounting. Financial Equity and Privacy, 1987-1988, 4 items. (Box-folder 8:7)
      Opinion and idea papers on equity and privacy; proposal for the use of taxonomy.
    - Office Council. Accounting. Financial Needs. Personal, 1974-1988, 17 items. (Box-folder 8:8)
      Policies about money for individuals; opinion and idea papers about personal money policy; personal money survey; proposal from planners; allowance for members; allowance input summary.
    - Office Council. Accounting. Leaving Fund, 1987-1989, 10 items. (Box-folder 8:9)
      Proposals and meetings on the Earned Leaving Fund (ELF); accounts of various leaving fund costs and members.
    - Office Council. Accounting. Loans and Insurance. Community, 1981-1983, 10 items. (Box-folder 8:10)
      Questions about long term borrowing; kitchen dining costs; information about Twin Oaks debts; opinion and idea paper about fire insurance and updates on medical insurance.
    - Office Council. Accounting. Loans. Personal, 1982-1986, 33 items. (Box-folder 8:11)
      Information on loans for departing and existing members; loan contract forms; loan requests; policies; opinion and idea papers
    - Office Council. Accounting. Loans. Personal, 1987-1996, 22 items. (Box-folder 8:12)
      Information on loans for departing and existing members; loan contract forms;loan requests; policies; opinion and idea papers.
    - Office Council. Accounting. Personal Money, 1984, 51 items. (Box-folder 8:13)
      Personal money surveys of Twin Oaks members.
    - Office Council. Accounting. Money Hole. Personal, 1985-1995, 10 items. (Box-folder 9:1)
      Policies; proposals; opinion and idea papers.
    - Office Council. Accounting. Vacation Earnings Policy, 1983-1984, 64 items. (Box-folder 9:2)
      Policies, proposals, and opinion and idea papers on vacation earnings; vacation earnings questionnaire and survey; meeting notes.
    - Office Council. Accounting. Vacation Earnings Policies, 1987-1998; n.d., 38 items. (Box-folder 9:3)
      Policies, proposals and opinion and idea papers on vacation earnings; vacation earnings questionnaire and survey; meeting notes.
    - Office Council. Accounting. Seniority Vacation Fund, 1986-1989, 8 items. (Box-folder 9:4)
      Proposal for vacation fund policy; roster of member seniority.
    - Office Council. Office. Computer Services, 1986-1989, 12 items. (Box-folder 9:5)
      Phone bill report; plan-writing budget worksheet; priority requests; meeting notes and opinion and idea papers.
    - Office Council. Office, 1983-1988, 9 items. (Box-folder 9:6)
      Opinion and idea papers on mailbox and mail system; postage planning budget worksheet; office supply policy.
  - J. Outreach Council
    - Outreach Council. Articles and Brochures about Twin Oaks, n.d., 25 items. (Box-folder 9:7)
      Articles about Twin Oaks, including A Special Community by Ed Gottlieb from the publication Sun Dial, Summer 1993; Community Living by Margaret Oaks; Eight Years After by Susan Oaks; It's The Community's Business by Larry Lenske and Mikki Wenig; Demystifying 'Man Made' Technology by Heidi and Joyce; Twin Oaks by Vince Zager; brochure with guidelines for visitors at Twin Oaks.
    - Outreach Council. Community Market, 1967-1972; n.d., 34 items. (Box-folder 9:8)
      Information about catalogs and products from the Community Market, a group of participating communes; invoices for paid accounts from Twin Oaks.
    - Outreach Council. Conferences, 1973-1988, 19 items. (Box-folder 9:9)
      Documents pertaining to conferences held and attended by Twin Oaks members.
    - Outreach Council. Conferences. Political, 1982-1983, 4 items. (Box-folder 9:10)
      Information on rural activists' conferences.
    - Outreach Council. Council Meeting Notes and Decisions, 1975-1988; n.d., 43 items. (Box-folder 10:1)
      Decision not to publish two publications; discussion of policies and procedures for visitors and members ranging from greetings to how to teach new skills.
    - Outreach Council. Federation of Egalitarian Communities, 1978-1985, 27 items. (Box-folder 10:2)
      Information about the Federation of Egalitarian Communities, a group of intentional communities spread out across North America; proposals; survey of responses from various communes' advertisements.
    - Outreach Council. Federation of Egalitarian Communities, 1985-1989; n.d., 43 items. (Box-folder 10:3)
      Constitution and by-laws; membership forms; discussion of nudity in brochures; correspondence; federation committee planning budget worksheet; job descriptions for secretary and facilitators.
    - Outreach Council. Federation of Egalitarian Communities. Anniversary 10th, 1986, 9 items. (Box-folder 10:4)
      Preparations for the tenth anniversary including requests for artwork and articles.
    - Outreach Council. Federation of Egalitarian Communities. Assembly, 1978-1991, 16 items. (Box-folder 10:5)
      Agendas, reports, and minutes from the Federation of Egalitarian Communities meetings.
    - Outreach Council. Federation of Egalitarian Communities. Brochures. Layouts and Bids, 1980-1985, 25 of items. (Box-folder 10:6)
    - Outreach Council. Federation of Egalitarian Communities. Businesses, 1983, 4 items. (Box-folder 10:7)
      Spreadsheet on hammock sales; advertisement for futons. OS Production Costs Variance Report.
    - Outreach Council. Federation of Egalitarian Communities. Photographs, n.d., 12 items. (Box-folder 10:8)
      Photographs and greeting cards.
    - Outreach Council. Federation of Egalitarian Communities. Publications, 1976-1987, 9 items. (Box-folder 10:9)
      Federation of Egalitarian Communities Newsletter; Inter communities Newsletter; Communion, Winter 1986; Communion, Spring 1986; Community Soundings, A Journal of Community, volume II, number 2; A Journal of Community, volume II, number III, December 21, 1987; A Journal of Community, First Anniversary Issue, March 21, 1986.
    - Outreach Council. Federation of Egalitarian Communities. Travel and Conference Papers, 1982-1988, 17 items. (Box-folder 10:10)
      Members travel all over the world to FEC Conferences and present papers that they have written.
    - Outreach Council. Federation of Egalitarian Communities. Urban Community, 1988, 4 items. (Box-folder 11:1)
      Proposal to develop an urban community.
    - Outreach Council. Federation of Intentional Communities, 1982-1990; n.d., 42 items. (Box-folder 11:2)
      Conferences and picnics; report of FIC meetings; by-laws of the FIC; list of other alternative societies. OS Medical expenditures chart.
    - Outreach Council. Federation of Intentional Communities. Intercommunities Network of Virginia, 1986-1990, 29 items. (Box-folder 11:3)
      Information on the Inter-communities Network, an informal association of intentional communities that share some common values; plans for gatherings and opportunities for recruitment with Shannon Farm, Springtree, Yogaville, North Mountain, Common Ground, Sojourners Orchard and Farm, Gesundheit Institute, Seven Oaks, and Innisfree Village; brochures and directories on the network and the participating communities.
    - Outreach Council. Growth, 1992, 6 items. (Box-folder 11:4)
      Survey of population and availability at Twin Oaks; reports indicating concerns about growth.
    - Outreach Council. Loan Solicitation, 1978-1979, 17 items. (Box-folder 11:5)
      Twin Oaks sends out a letter to publications asking friends to lend them money.
    - Outreach Council. Local Relations, 1977; 1982-1985, 29 items. (Box-folder 11:6)
      Information about volunteering local services; policies about neighbors; incidents with neighbors; political opinions; public library service and Twin Oaks; compromises among Twin Oaks residents. OS letter to members regarding Louisa Supervisor.
    - Outreach Council. Local Relations, 1986-1989; n.d., 21 items. (Box-folder 11:7)
      Program for a local talent show; community service opportunities; note about housing a homeless teenager; notes against purchasing guns; local relations planning budget sheet; letter from a local church thanking Twin Oaks for a received donation; certificate for citizen service from Louisa Against Litter Council.
    - Outreach Council. Newsletter and Community Publications Cooperative, 1984-1988; n.d., 9 items. (Box-folder 11:8)
      Requests for articles and artwork; budget planning worksheet.
    - Outreach Council. Recruitment, 1980-1989, 54 items. (Box-folder 11:9)
      Meeting notes; proposals and ideas; procedures for becoming a member; member issues; recruiting women.
    - Outreach Council. Recruitment. Correspondence and Advertisements, 1968-1969, 46 items. (Box-folder 11:10)
      Letters to newspapers and periodicals advertising Twin Oaks; correspondence with other communes for recruiting purposes; discussion about being included in Arthur Frommer's Travel Almanac 1988; planning budget worksheet.
    - Outreach Council. School of Living, 1987-1988, 6 items. (Box-folder 11:11)
      Meeting reports and informational packets regarding The School of Living, a tax-exempt, philanthropic, and educational network
    - Outreach Council. Unitarian Universalist Association, 1976-1989, 16 items. (Box-folder 11:12)
      Brochures and information about the Unitarian Universalist Twin Oaks fellowship that provides educational opportunities to community children; proposal to recruit a Unitarian Universalist minister.
    - Outreach Council. Urban Community, 1987-1989, 7 items. (Box-folder 11:13)
      Several proposals for a new community inside the city of Charlottesville.
    - Outreach Council. Visitor. Controversial Reporter, 1987-1988, 11 items. (Box-folder 12:1)
      Information pertaining to a controversial reporter's stay at Twin Oaks.
    - Outreach Council. Visitor Program, 1980-1987, 32 items. (Box-folder 12:2)
      Policies; meeting notes; glossary of terms; guidelines for visitors.
    - Outreach Council. Visitor Program, 1988-1989, 22 items. (Box-folder 12:3)
    - Outreach Council. Visitor Questionnaires, 1984-1986, 88 items. (Box-folder 12:4)
      Questionnaires about how the visitors heard about Twin Oaks with questions about their health and length of visit.
    - Outreach Council. Visitor Questionnaire Analysis, 1982-1985; n.d., 27 items. (Box-folder 12:5)
      Summary and analysis of responses.
    - Outreach Council. Visitor Schedule, 1985-1986, Charts and schedules involving visitors to Twin Oaks. (Box-folder 12:6)
    - Outreach Council. Visitor Tours, 1981-1982; 1984; 1987, 7 items. (Box-folder 12:7)
      Correspondence from visitors thanking members for the tour; information about the difficulties of giving tours; Rainbow Family wants to borrow space to have a gathering at Twin Oaks.
    - Outreach Council. Women and Twin Oaks, [1982], 23 items. (Box-folder 12:8)
      Proposal for a slideshow to recruit more women; an article about Twin Oaks titled Indigenous Socialism in the United States, A Feminist Perspective on Intentional Creation of Alternative Community by Batya Winbaums; articles with interviews of women at Twin Oaks and at East Wind.
    - Outreach Council. Other Communities. The Abode of the Message [Retreats], 1978; 1982; n.d., 5 items. (Box-folder 12:9)
      Sufi Retreat Center brochure; correspondence between communities; list of retreats.
    - Outreach Council. Other Communities. Abrahamic Community, 1981-1982, 3 items. (Box-folder 12:10)
      Newsletters.
    - Outreach Council. Other Communities. Aloe Community, 1976-1979; n.d., 5 items and 14 photographs. (Box-folder 12:11)
      Photographs; description of Aloe Community; Federation of Egalitarian Communities Newsletter; correspondence about a disagreement between Another Way Community and Aloe.
    - Outreach Council. Other Communities. Alpha Farm, 1978-1988, 7 items. (Box-folder 12:12)
      Brochures about Alpha Farm; correspondence between Twin Oaks and the Alpha Farm, the Federation of Egalitarian Communities, and East Wind.
    - Outreach Council. Other Communities. Ananda Cooperative Village, 1977; 1981-1982; 1988, 8 items and 1 photograph. (Box-folder 12:13)
      Brochures; a photograph.
    - Outreach Council. Other Communities. Appletree, 1981-1988, 8 items and 35 photographs. (Box-folder 12:14)
      Brochures; notes on fertility; correspondence between Appletree and Twin Oaks.
    - Outreach Council. Other Communities. Aprovecho Rural Center, 1988 September, 2 items. (Box-folder 13:1)
      Brochures.
    - Outreach Council. Other Communities. Aquarian Research Foundation, 1982-1989; n.d., 11 items. (Box-folder 13:2)
      Letter from a former member about the possibility of starting a new cooperative living group; information about journalist Art Rosenblum and The Peace Factory; Aquarian Alternatives Newsletters including an article by Art Rosenblum.
    - Outreach Council. Other Communities. Baker Branch, 1988-1989, 1 item. (Box-folder 13:3)
      Happy Winter Holidays letter to Twin Oaks.
    - Outreach Council. Other Communities. Bear Tribe, 1981; 1986; n.d., 6 items. (Box-folder 13:4)
      Bear Tribe catalog; Bear Tribe activities; letter from the editor of the Bear Tribe; press releases about publications by the Bear Tribe; list of products from the Bear Tribe.
    - Outreach Council. Other Communities. Breitenbush Community, 1986; 1988, 12 items. (Box-folder 13:5)
      Correspondence with Twin Oaks; The Breitenbush Newsletter; advertisement for cooks; literature and applications; map.
    - Outreach Council. Other Communities. Bruderhof Communities, 1986-1989, 14 items. (Box-folder 13:6)
      Correspondence with Twin Oaks; an article titled The 400-Year-Old Commune by Jon Swan; an article titled A New Hutterian Community Was Founded in the publication Kibbutz Studies, February 1987; Bruderhof communities publications, The Plough, numbers 15 and 17-20; The Plough Catalog 1988-1989.
    - Outreach Council. Other Communities. The Builders Community, 1987-1988, 9 items. (Box-folder 13:7)
      Information about the Builders Community; publications of the Builders Quarterly 1987-1988.
    - Outreach Council. Other Communities. Camphill Village, 1982; 1985-1986, 11 items. (Box-folder 13:8)
      Brochures; newsletters and other literature on Camphill Village; annual reports.
    - Outreach Council. Other Communities. Cerro Gordo, 1978-1980; 1982, 16 items. (Box-folder 13:9)
      Brochures and newsletters; The Town Forum Community Report; The Cerro Gordo News, 1979-1980 and 1982.
    - Outreach Council. Other Communities. Chinook Learning Community, 1980, 3 items. (Box-folder 13:10)
    - Outreach Council. Other Communities. Chrysalis Community, 1981-1985, 14 items and 2 photographs. (Box-folder 13:11)
      Correspondence about the Chrysalis Community joining the Federation of Egalitarian Communities; legal contracts; brochures and articles.
    - Outreach Council. Other Communities. Circle Pines Center, 1979, 2 items. (Box-folder 13:12)
      Brief description of the center; a publication, Pine Needles, Summer Camp edition volume 40, number 1, 1979.
    - Outreach Council. Other Communities. City of the Sun Foundation, 1988, 3 items. (Box-folder 13:13)
      Brochures; newsletter The Golden Dawn.
    - Outreach Council. Other Communities. Coldfoot Creek Community, 1987, 4 items. (Box-folder 13:14)
      Correspondence giving introduction; brochures.
    - Other Communities. The Collective Networker Newsletter, 1986-1988, 5 items. (Box-folder 13:15)
      Five editions of The Collective Networker Newsletter.
    - Outreach Council. Other Communities. Communities in General, n.d., 5 items. (Box-folder 13:16)
      Article titled Making Communities Work featuring an interview with David Thatcher in Simply Living; resources for information on intentional communities; publication titled Communes Network Directory.
    - Outreach Council. Other Communities. Communities of the Ark, 1985 January, 1 item. (Box-folder 13:17)
      Newsletter.
    - Outreach Council. Other Communities. Community of Hospitality, 1986 May, 1 item. (Box-folder 13:18)
    - Outreach Council. Other Communities. Community Service, Inc., 1978-1981; 1984-1988, 25 items. (Box-folder 13:19)
      Brochures; questionnaire; list of resource books; Community Service Newsletters.
    - Outreach Council. Other Communities. Currents Community, 1986 January, 2 items. (Box-folder 13:20)
      Literature and policies.
    - Outreach Council. Other Communities. Dandelion Community, 1982; 1985; 1987-1988, 18 items, 24 photographs and transparencies. (Box-folder 14:1)
      Brochures; correspondence with Twin Oaks; articles and reports.
    - Outreach Council. Other Communities. Dragonfly Farm, 1988, 3 items. (Box-folder 14:2)
      Photographs; map and introduction paper.
    - Outreach Council. Other Communities. Dunmire Hollow, 1986, 2 items. (Box-folder 14:3)
      Information on the Dunmire Hollow Spring Fling and map.
    - Outreach Council. Other Communities. The Earth Community Network, 1983-1984, 3 items. (Box-folder 14:4)
    - Outreach Council. Other Communities. East Wind, 1976-1989, 48 items. (Box-folder 14:5)
      Articles; planners meeting notes; trade-off game reports; newsletters; correspondence; opinion and idea papers.
    - Outreach Council. Other Communities. East Wind, 1976-1989, 71 items and photographs. (Box-folder 14:6)
      Newspaper articles; planners meeting notes; new member information and charts; newsletters; opinion and idea papers about labor and employment; photographs.
    - Outreach Council. Other Communities. Eden Community, n.d., 1 item. (Box-folder 14:7)
      An article titled The Community of Eden published by the Eden Community.
    - Outreach Council. Other Communities. The Emissary Communities, 1981-1987, 5 items. (Box-folder 14:8)
      Brochure; press release; newsletters titled Integrity International.
    - Outreach Council. Other Communities. End of the Road Farm Community, n.d., 1 item. (Box-folder 14:9)
      Brochure.
    - Outreach Council. Other Communities. The Farm, 1976-1983; 1984, 12 items. (Box-folder 14:10)
      Newspaper articles; copies of the publications Plenty and New Age.
    - Outreach Council. Other Communities. The Fellowship of the Inner Light, 1960; 1979, 8 items. (Box-folder 14:11)
      Various publications relating to The Fellowship of the Inner Light and their beliefs.
    - Outreach Council. Other Communities. Fruitlands (Transcendentalist Communal Experience), 1973, 1 item. (Box-folder 14:12)
      An article in The New York Times about the transcendentalist commune.
    - Outreach Council. Other Communities. Ganas, 1985-1986, 2 items. (Box-folder 14:13)
      One community service newsletter; excerpts of a letter from [Allen] to Twin Oaks member [Laird] within the commune.
    - Outreach Council. Other Communities. Gesundheit, 1982-1985, 15 items. (Box-folder 14:14)
      Various newsletters; informational leaflets; flyers for the Gesundheit Institute.
    - Outreach Council. Other Communities. Grey Gables, 1973-1974, 1 item. (Box-folder 14:15)
      One bound Journal of Grey Gables Community.
    - Outreach Council. Other Communities. Hailos Community, n.d., 2 items. (Box-folder 15:1)
      One brochure for the community; one scrapbook page with two pictures.
    - Outreach Council. Other Communities. Harbin Hot Springs, 1984, 2 items. (Box-folder 15:2)
      One informational leaflet; one article about the commune.
    - Outreach Council. Other Communities. Heathcote Center, 1979, 1 item. (Box-folder 15:3)
      Directory listing for the commune in the Guide to Cooperative Alternatives.